<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Profano-mastix. Or, a briefe and necessarie direction concerning the respects which wee owe to God, and his house even in outward worship, and reverent using of holy places. Shewing chiefly when, and how, wee ought to enter; how to behave our selves being entred, how to depart; as also, how to esteeme of Gods house at every other time. Written out of a true and sincere intent to reduce the disordered and factious, to a better order then either their neglect, stubbornnesse, or scrupulositie can purchase for them. / By Iohn Swan curate of Duxford S. Peters.</title>
            <author>Swan, John, d. 1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23513</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106202</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898288</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898288</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6542</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73284)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6542)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1337:1; 2086:1a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Profano-mastix. Or, a briefe and necessarie direction concerning the respects which wee owe to God, and his house even in outward worship, and reverent using of holy places. Shewing chiefly when, and how, wee ought to enter; how to behave our selves being entred, how to depart; as also, how to esteeme of Gods house at every other time. Written out of a true and sincere intent to reduce the disordered and factious, to a better order then either their neglect, stubbornnesse, or scrupulositie can purchase for them. / By Iohn Swan curate of Duxford S. Peters.</title>
                  <author>Swan, John, d. 1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 61, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by I. D[awson]. and are to be sold by Daniel Pakeman, at the signe of the Raine-bow in Fleet-street neere the Temple gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Variant: pagination [8], 61, [3], 11, [1] p. which includes "An appendix for further satisfaction" which has a separate dated title page and separate pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Copy at reel 2086 variant; bound with STC 23515.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sacred space --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6542:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6542:1"/>
            <p>PROFANO-MASTIX.</p>
            <p>OR, A BRIEFE AND Neceſſarie Direction concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the reſpects which wee owe to God, and his Houſe, even in outward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and reverent uſing of Holy Places.</p>
            <p>Shewing chiefly When, and How, wee ought to enter; How to behave our ſelves being Entred, How to Depart; as alſo, How to eſteeme of Gods Houſe at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other time.</p>
            <p>Written out of a true and ſincere intent to teduce the Diſordered and Factious, to a better order then either their neglect, ſtubbornneſſe, or ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſitie can purchaſe for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> IOHN SWAN Curate of <hi>Duxford S. Peters.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GEN. 28.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>How dreadfull is this place. This is no other but the Houſe of God, and the Gate of Heaven.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Daniel Pakeman,</hi> at the ſigne of the Raine-bow in Fleet-ſtreet neere the Temple gate. 1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6542:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6542:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Worſhipfull M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THONIE TOPHAM, Doctour of Divinitie, and Deane of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> all health and happineſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N token of that humble reſpect which I owe to your ſelfe, I am bold to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate theſe poore endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to you; hoping that as my ſtudies long agoe abetted by your furtherance, ſo a tribute of their fruits ſhall bee now accepted at your worthy hands: for though I reckon my ſelfe bound to
<pb facs="tcp:6542:3"/>render more than what's contained in theſe few papers, yet (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>non Minus regium ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> humanitatis, parva lubenti facili<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuſcipere animo, quam magna largiri.</hi> And this I ſhall the rather hope, becauſe herein I have chiefly laboured to caſt out that filth and rubbiſh, wherewith the Philiſtims have ſtopped <hi>Abrahams</hi> wells: for they bee not the ancient, but the later times againſt which wee find a juſt complaint. And I would to God there were no cauſe: But (alaſſe) 'tis otherwiſe; inſomuch that hee now is ſaid to bee unſound, who will not ſide with factious oppoſites, nor yeeld to ſoothe the idle fancies, and needleſſe feares of not a few. But as to a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mouth all things reliſh with a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:6542:3"/>taſt, <hi>Oris non elementi vitio;</hi> ſo things wholeſome and good, appeare contrarie to corrupt judgements: and therefore it makes not much what ſuch men cenſure; eſpecially the Author being ſheltered under the favourable wing of your protection, which cannot but adde more life to the warrantable proceedings of him who wiſheth both your happineſſe here and glorie hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, And ſhall ever remaine at your ſervice to be commanded,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IOHN SWAN.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Novemb. <hi>5. 1638.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6542:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6542:4"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Hope (ere long) to befriend thee with a worke of better worth, if this (in the meane time) may find thee cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in the acceptation. Sure I am, that in it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, it cannot out bee jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſſarie labour: For, whilſt it ſeekes the pacification of contentious ſpirits, by ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to give ſatisfaction concerning ſome things now in agitation, it aymes at Gods glorie; the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of whoſe worſhip hath by degrees, growne to ſuch a ſordid and homely paſſe, as Religion hath (now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes) loſt much of that bright beautie, which in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges heretofore ſhee was knowne to have. But I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the words of that wiſe King, <hi>Solomon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.10.</note> Say not thou, What is the cauſe that the former dayes were better then theſe? for thou doſt not enquire wiſely concerning this. Which is as if it ſhould bee ſaid; Late times may be as good as ancient, if Men were but willing to tread in the ſame ſteps that they have trod: for the neerer a fountaine, the better the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Stand therefore upon the wayes (as the Prophet ſpeaketh;) and conſider: aske of the old wayes,<note place="margin">Ier. 6.57.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:6542:5"/>which is the beſt. And verely, among reformed Churches, there is none deſires it more then Ours; and might be happy in it, if wee had among us no filthy Vipers. But theſe as they are enemies to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; ſo alſo to others: for whilſt ſome doe not only diſobey, but defend their Diſobedience, they poyſon many more both by their example and Defence. And what though they gaine a popular applauſe in their envious proceedings againſt the Church? this is but to make a bad caſe worſe: For one man of judgement is better by farre, then a numerous multitude of the common ſort; whoſe very wiſdome is but as a light feather in matters of this nature, as being too farre above their reach. It were good therefore that the Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſcribe beyond his Laſt; nor no man meddle but in his right <hi>Vb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> for till then, there will bee no end of Schiſme nor Diſorder; And ſo, no quiet to the Church of God here planted among us. I ſay no more, but wiſh every ſocietie to pray for the peace of their Holy Mother:<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.6.</note> for (as it is written in the Booke of Pſalmes) <hi>They which love her ſhall proſper.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6542:5"/>
            <head>PROFANO-MASTIX; OR, A TREATISE FOR DIRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction concerning the reſpects which we owe to God and his houſe, even in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip, and reverent uſing of holy places.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Man that hath but an indifferent inſight into the poyſonſome humours of head-ſtrong Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick's, and ſuch as are daily infected by them, may eaſily diſcerne, that their affectation of paritie ends not in perſons; but is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred even to places alſo: whereupon it comes to paſſe, that they doe as ſleightly eſteeme of Churches, as of common and ordinary pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and of things ſacred, as of things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane. But they may bee aſhamed (if any ſhame at all be left them) thus to revive and foſter the condemned hereſie of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rius</hi> on the one ſide, and of the <hi>Euſtaſians</hi> on the other ſide. For whilſt they ſtand thus affected, they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6542:6"/>doe equally give life and nouriſhment to the dead ſpirits of each of thoſe forenamed he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</p>
            <p>And firſt concerning their Paritie which they would have among men of the Church, how diſſonant it is to Orthodox doctrine, <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in particular, beſides the generall ſtreame of other Fathers, have ſufficiently declared: Inſomuch, that if even S. <hi>Hierome</hi> himſelfe in any of his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings ſeemeth to ſay any thing which may bee thought not to jumpe directly, with what the other Fathers, and Scriptures have taught con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this; it is truly and modeſtly imputed to him, by that learned<note n="*" place="margin">Saravia de diverſ. Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. gradibus.</note> 
               <hi>Saravia,</hi> as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate opinion, wherein hee favoured too much, that which was condemned in him already mentioned; I meane <hi>Ae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rius.</hi> Now may a man but appeale from S. <hi>Hierom</hi> in one place, to S. <hi>Hierom</hi> in another place: for writing <hi>contra Luciferianos,</hi> hee affirmeth plainly, that the Church of God conſiſteth of many degrees, the higheſt whereof he makes to reſt in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: and they,<note place="margin">Ignatius Epiſt. ad Smyrn. Diony fius ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. <hi>Hier.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> as S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> (the diſciple of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> (the ſcholer of S. <hi>Paul</hi>) have declared, are terminated in Chriſt imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately. In a word; as the 70 diſciples were inferiour to the Apoſtles; ſo bee ordinarie Prieſts now to the Biſhops: for as they ſucceed the Apoſtles; ſo doe inferiour Prieſts the 70 diſciples. Which if it had beene croſſe to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6542:6"/>divine inſtitution, neither would S. <hi>Paul</hi> have created <hi>Timothie</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> Biſhops; the one of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the other of <hi>Crete:</hi> nor would the ſpirit of God but have cryed out againſt it, when thoſe ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> were ſharply taxed for their faults: For certaine it is, that albeit they were governed by Biſhops, yet is there nothing ſpoken againſt either their admitting, or retaining of ſuch a government. Nay let me adde, that <hi>Philip</hi> preached, and baptized, and converted <hi>Samaria;</hi> but had not the power to ordaine them Paſtours: and therefore <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> are ſent to impoſe hands, and give the holy Ghoſt; as in the eighth chapter of the Acts of the Apoſtles may be read at large.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, concerning Gods houſe, that it ſhould not be differenced from another place, was (a long while ſince) the prophane opinion of the <hi>Euſtaſian</hi> hereticks, and of the <hi>Meſſalians</hi> after them. But, that the ſtreame of this filthy wickedneſſe might be the better ſtopped, this we know,<note place="margin">This Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell was in the yeare of our Lord 324.</note> that about 1313 years ſince, at <hi>Gangra,</hi> a towne in <hi>Paphlagonia,</hi> there was a Councell held; wherein this heretick was confuted, and hee, with the reſt of his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, accurſed. The Fathers of which Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, in their ſubſcription after their Canons, among other things, have theſe words; Wee honour (ſay they) the houſes of God, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies which are in them, as holy and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6542:7"/>
            <p>And afterwards, in the daies of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, there was a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> Canon 38. To which our 18 Canon well agreeth, and both to that of S. <hi>Paul</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> Canon made in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Towrs,</hi> wherein the people were requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to behave themſelves reverently in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. And in the next Canon of the ſaid Councell (as alſo in the Councell of <hi>Mentz,</hi> which was celebrated in the ſame yeare) no Iudgement ſeats might be allowed to be either in Churches or their porches. And in the 48 Canon of that at <hi>Mentz,</hi> there was order ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that no wanton ſongs might bee ſung neere unto a Church:<note place="margin">Canon 52:</note> Nor might any one (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a Biſhop or worthy Prieſt, or a religious faithfull Laick) bee buried in a Church. The like things were done at the Councell of <hi>Arles:</hi> ſo alſo in the Councell of <hi>Starburg,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Canon 17.</note> which was 86 yeares after it.</p>
            <p>Long before which times of <hi>Charles,</hi> the Emperour <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Evag lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> about the yeare of our Lord God<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius</hi> in Chron.</note> 534. would not receive into his Treaſurie the veſſels of gold which <hi>Titus</hi> took out of the Temple, when it was deſtroyed; but ſent them to the Chriſtian Biſhops of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> there to bee diſpoſed of, as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thought meete. There was a Councell afterwards, <hi>viz.</hi> the third Councell of <hi>Bracara</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Helvic. &amp; Alſted. in Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> about the yeare of our Lord 675. which tooke order alſo concerning holy veſſels: for, in the ſecond Canon of the ſaid Councell, it was decreed; that Veſſels dedicated to God, ſhould not be abuſed, nor applyed to ſecular and humane uſes.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:6542:7"/>
            <p>Neither is it but to be admired, how zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous the Emperour <hi>Conſtantinus Magnus</hi> was:<note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſt. libr. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>56.</hi> Et So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> for, being about to make warre with the <hi>Perſians;</hi> hee cauſed a Tabernacle or moving Temple to be made to carry with him, that thereby he might alwayes have a holy place, and houſe for his God, ſanctified and prepared for religious worſhip. Nor may this ſeeme ſtrange: for as the <hi>Iewes</hi> had a moving houſe for their God, ſutable to their owne condition whilſt they lived in their Tents: So he, being to goe from home, provided a Tabernacle to doe his worſhip in; whereas, at other times, he had ſtanding Temples, or Churches, and theſe built (even for their forme of fabrick) in ſome ſort imitable to their fixed Temple at <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi> For the primitive Chriſtians were ſuch followers of Antiquitie, rather then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliners unto noveltie, that they built their Churches with ſuch diſtinction of Courts and places (although not for the ſame uſes) as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> did his Temple. For as the <hi>Iewes</hi> had their <hi>Atrium exterius,</hi> their <hi>Atrium interius, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum,</hi> and <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum;</hi> ſo had the firſt Chriſtians their <hi>Locus Poenitentium, Auditori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, presbyterium</hi> and <hi>Sacrarium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, to goe a little higher;<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Philip</hi> favoured the Chriſtians, and would have gladly joyned with them, hee might not bee permitted ſuddenly, untill hee had firſt ſtood in <hi>Loco poenitentium,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6542:8"/>in many things hee was ſtill faultie.</p>
            <p>Nay, higher yet: for in the dayes of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had prophaned the Church which was at <hi>Corinth,</hi> they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended for it.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>Shall I praiſe you in this (ſaith the Apoſtle) I praiſe you not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howbeit things are now growne to ſuch a paſſe, that if God bee not ſerved ſlovenly, wee are judged to be guiltie of ſuperſtition, or Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie. Or, if wee reſpect the Church as the houſe of God, and will not ſuffer it to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned, nor come into it but with feare and reverence; then wee are all for Poperie, and I cannot tell what.<note place="margin">L. Archbiſh. of <hi>Canterb.</hi> ſpeech in Star-Cham. <hi>Iune</hi> 14. 1637.</note> But I pray God (ſaith our chiefe and reverend Prelate) that the time come not upon this Kingdome, in which it will be found, that no one thing hath advanced, or uſhered in Poperie ſo faſt, as the groſſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities even in the worſhip of God, which theſe men, and their like, maintaine both in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and practiſe. And certainely, this is a feare which ſtands upon too good a ground: Slight it not therefore; but rather eſteeme that to bee a religious care, which earneſtly deſires a timely prevention. For as another (once alſo a maine pillar of Gods Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us) hath diſcovered, there is nothing which doth more retaine many in recuſancie, then want of due reverence in the houſe of God,<note place="margin">Biſh. <hi>Andr.</hi> in a Sermon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.10.</note> and at his holy worſhip. I am privie (ſaith he) there is no one thing doth more
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6542:8"/>alien thoſe, that of a ſimple mind refuſe the Church, then this; that they ſee ſo unſeemly behaviour, ſo ſmall reverence ſhewed this way. But ſure, the Apoſtle<note n="*" place="margin">See the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.25.</note> telleth us, our cariage there ſhould be ſuch, ſo decent, as if a ſtranger, or unbeleever ſhould come into our aſſemblies, the very reverence hee ſeeth there ſhould make him fall downe and ſay, <hi>Verely God is among us;</hi> to ſee us ſo reſpectively beare ourſelves, in the manner of our worſhip. And therefore though<note n="*" place="margin">Hee was an Ambaſſadour in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of King <hi>James</hi> his raigne for K. <hi>Henry</hi> 4. of <hi>France.</hi> See the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court. pag. 38.</note> Marqueſſe <hi>Roſney</hi> ſpoke home and fully, in regard of what hee ſaw at the Court and <hi>Canterbury</hi> (viz. <hi>That if the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches in France had kept the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders among them that wee have, hee was aſſured there would have beene in that Countrie many thouſand Proteſtants at that time more then there were.</hi>) Yet had he come into our ordinary pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Churches, hee would have ſurely ſaid, There is much wanting in that reverent beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour which is required of devout worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and more Proteſtants might bee in <hi>England,</hi> if all places were alike ordered. Give mee leave therefore to inſiſt upon five things concerning our aſſemblies, or worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God in his houſe: and one more to be regarded at all times elſe; aſwell when there is no Aſſemblie, as when there is.</p>
            <p>The five be theſe. Firſt, that at the time of publick worſhip, wee be not <hi>Late commers.</hi> Secondly, that we be not <hi>Ill Enterers.</hi> Thirdly,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6542:9"/>that our deportment, at the time of our being there, be reverent. Fourthly, that our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be not till all be ended. And then, laſt of all, that it be ſuch as becommeth thoſe who are going to their owne houſes from the houſe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I ſhall take them in order. The firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes our late comming, which is an ill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and a ſore evill; for they that bee back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in their ſervice to God, are a great way behind in the way to heaven; and to preferre their owne fancies before godly orders, is to decline the ſteps of pious leaders. And of this they are guiltie, who be dull in their approach to the houſe of God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 87.2.</note> For, as the Lord loveth the gates of Sion, more then all the dwellings of <hi>Iacob;</hi> ſo the Children of God delight to bee there, as knowing that then they are come before him, in a more ſpeciall manner, then when they were at home in their owne houſes. Yea, and as they doe deſire the heaven that is above: So alſo to be one with thoſe in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven beneath. For that the Congregations of the Church militant, is a kind of heaven upon earth, is more then manifeſt: and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> (I doe beleeve) hath an eye thereunto, in that ſacred booke of the Revelation. Thus it was with <hi>David:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.2.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is athirſt for God; yea, even for the living God: Oh when ſhall I come and appeare before the preſence of God.</hi> And in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Pſalme; I was glad when they ſaid unto
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6542:9"/>me, <hi>Let us goe into the houſe of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 122.1:</note> And in the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> it is foretold as a token of the flouriſhing eſtate of Chriſts Church, that many people ſhall ſay,<note place="margin">Eſay 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>O come, Let us goe up to the mountaine of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of Iacob.</hi> And in the Proverbs there is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing promiſed to them <hi>who ſeeke wiſdome early:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 8.17 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as alſo to thoſe <hi>who watch daily at her gates, and waite at the Poſts of her doores.</hi> And in the <hi>Acts,</hi> the good Chriſtians <hi>were altogether with one accord in one place.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Acts 4.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The neglect whereof is no ſigne of true zeale, but a motive rather to ſtirre up the coactive power of Governours to compell them to come in, when they are called, that Gods houſe may be filled. It was ſo in the Parable, and muſt be ſo alſo in every particular Congregation. I find it therefore ordered in the antient Church of Chriſt, that they which came not in the beginning ſhould be ſubject to cenſure, as well as thoſe who were abſent, or as they who departed away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all was ended. To which purpoſe the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of <hi>Caſsian,</hi> and forty ſeventh Canon of the Councell of <hi>Agatha</hi> is fitly alledged.</p>
            <p>But beſides that ſloth, which a ſlight regard of Gods houſe begets in many (as well Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries, as other careleſſe Chriſtians) what doe I alſo heare? Nothing more, then that our prayers are common; And what of that? They are but as they ought; The Church of God would never order that they ſhould bee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6542:10"/>other.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>18.</hi> in <hi>2</hi> Cor. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> Our prayers (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) are common; for all ſay the ſame prayer. The reaſon whereof is given by certaine Councels, <hi>Ne forte aliquid contra fidem, vel per ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, vel per minus ſtudium ſit compoſitum;</hi> Leſt perchance ſomething might bee done through ignorance or eareleſneſſe, which might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the faith; as is expreſſed in the twelfth Canon of the <hi>Milevitan</hi> Councell, in the yeare of our Lord 402. At which Councell S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> was preſent: For among others that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, there was <hi>Aurelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo.</hi> Five yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which, the third Councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> was<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare 397.</note> celebrated; (there alſo was <hi>Auguſtine:</hi>) and in the 23 Canon thereof, it was decreed, that not any prayers ſhould bee uſed in the Congregations, but ſuch as had beene former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly approved.<note place="margin">See Math. 6.7.8.9. &amp; Math. 23.14.</note> Neither is all this but agreeable to our Saviours meaning; who (becauſe hee delighted not in vaine bablings) taught his Diſciples to make uſe, both of a ſhort and ſet forme? And alſo how unfitting it ever was, to give way to private fancies in a publike aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie, S. <hi>Paul</hi> declareth; For when yee come together, how is it (ſaith hee) that every one hath a Pſalme,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.26.</note> hath a doctrine, hath a tongue, hath a revelation? Let all things bee done to edifying: Long before which times, it was the counſell of <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Let thy words bee few:</hi> for God regardeth not our prayers according to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6542:10"/>their length; but according to their ſtrength and pithineſſe. And indeed to have ſhort formes, and often ejaculations, ſhewes the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſſe of the ſpirit, and is to be truly inſtant in prayer; to aske, to ſeeke, to knock.</p>
            <p>Dare any therefore be ſo bold, as to vilifie the ſhort and pithy prayers of the Church, and thereupon perſwade the ſimple that they have juſt cauſe to bee rardie commers? Dare they affirme that they are but ſhreds and pieces, and not worthy the name of prayers; and that in the Letanie is a kind of conjuring? Prophane wretches as they are, to bee thus diſordered: They might eaſily perceive, if they were not blind, that the Church goes piouſly to worke, according to the rule of Gods holy word: and may be no more blamed, no not for her <hi>Lord have mercy on us, Chriſt have mercy on us, Lord have mercy on us,</hi> and the like ſhort ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger requeſts; no more (I ſay) then our Saviour blamed the good woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi> devout <hi>Bartimeus,</hi> or told us that the humble Publican diſpleaſed God, when hee ſaid no more but,<note place="margin">See Math. 15.22.15. Mark, 10.48. Luke 18.13.</note> 
               <hi>God be mercifull to me a ſinner:</hi> An admonition yet (I hope) may come in time. Let theſe people therefore take heed, that God wipe not out their names out of the Booke of life; for ſcorning that Booke which containes the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the living God: in which I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing contrary to his holy Word. Nay, rather this I know, that it well agreeth to the holy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6542:11"/>Scriptures; and in the ſubſtance, forme, and order thereof, to the formes of the ancient Church; containing things, not only of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe, but of abſolute neceſſitie. For (that I may the better invite thee) let mee plead the cauſe a little further. Doſt thou deſire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe thy ſinnes? there's a forme of exquiſite confeſſion. Or doſt thou deſire to bee abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? there's an order how the Prieſt ſhall ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the truly penitent and faithfull ſoule. Or doſt thou deſire to praiſe thy God? there's an heavenly <hi>Te Deum</hi> for ſuch a purpoſe? or doſt thou deſire to make an open confeſſion of that faith which the orthodox Chriſtians ever held? there be the three Creeds; namely, that of the Apoſtles, <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and the <hi>Niceene</hi> Creed: the two laſt of which are received of the Church, not as new, but as expoſitions of the firſt. Their foundation is in Scripture, and are <hi>Regula fidei,</hi> even as the Decalogue is <hi>Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la vitae.</hi> Or doſt thou deſire to pray as thy Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our teacheth? there's the <hi>Pater noſter,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Doctor <hi>Boyſe</hi> in his Poſt.</note> A prayer which excells all other in many reſpects; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpels epitome, compiled by wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it ſelfe: ſo large for matter, ſo ſhort for phraſe, ſo ſweet for order, as that it deſerveth worthily to have the Firſt and Moſt place in all our Liturgie. The firſt, ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> as guide to the reſt. The moſt, ſaith that learned <hi>Hooker,</hi> as a neceſſary complement to ſupplie whatſoever is wanting in the reſt: This being
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6542:11"/>
               <hi>tanquam ſal,</hi> as a kind of Salt to ſeaſon all and every part of the divine ſervice?<note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> In which regard (ſaith our Engliſh Poſtiller) we uſe it often, as at the end of the Letanie, at the end of Baptiſme, at the end of the Communion, and at the end of other ſacred actions. Or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, doſt thou deſire to give publike thanks (as a good Chriſtian ought to doe) for publike benefits, or to bee eaſed from generall calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or to bee ſecured from common evils? why there, in that booke, be formes and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes for ſuch a purpoſe, yea, for the asking of thoſe things which bee requiſite and neceſſary as well for the bodie as the ſoule.</p>
            <p>And will none of theſe things move thee to come betimes to Gods houſe? I doubt thy ſanctitie, and ſuſpect thy ſoundneſſe. The place is holy, the ſervice holy: And therefore let there bee ſo much holineſſe in thee, as may bring thee cheerefully, early and devoutly to this holy place; and there make thee to be one with the reſt in that holy buſineſſe, which well beſeemes a holy Chriſtian. For this is certaine, that our holineſſe towards God concernes us one way, in that wee are men, and another way, in that wee are joyned as parts to that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible myſticall body, which is his Church. As men we are at our owne choyce, both for time, and place, and forme, according to the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of our owne occaſions in private. But as we be the members of a publike body, the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6542:12"/>ſervice which is to be done of us, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie be publike; And ſo conſequently bee performed by us on holy dayes, and in holy places. And thus I have done with the firſt thing; which is, that wee be not late com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond concernes our Reverence in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring: which, how it ought (of right) to bee performed, by degrees ſhall be declared.</p>
            <p>In the Scriptures you know that wee reade of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> that they did their reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at the very doore of the Tabernacle, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.6. And, take heed to thy foot when thou entreſt into the houſe of God, is the wiſe mans counſell in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1. Hee forewarnes thee, that hee might fore-arme thee. And good reaſon that his counſell ſhould bee regarded; otherwiſe the heart that thou bringeſt with thee, is no better then <hi>cor fatui,</hi> a fooles heart: enough to make a man be guiltie of evill, when hee ſhould bee doing of good. It is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſay, that although ſuch outward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was requiſite under the Law; yet not now required. For before Iudaiſme began, <hi>Iacob</hi> acknowledged <hi>Bethel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 28.</note> the houſe of God, to bee a place of feare and reverence. Hee did no ſooner perceive that it was an houſe of God, but hee preſently began to bee perplexed, for feare he had not behaved himſelfe ſo in it, as of right he knew hee ought to doe in all ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And albeit our Saviour ſaid to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6542:12"/>of <hi>Samaria</hi> in the fourth chapter of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> that the time was then at hand, that God ſhould not be worſhipped either at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> or at mount <hi>Garazim;</hi> but that the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers ſhould worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in truth; yet did hee not ſay any thing for the aboliſhing of publike Places, purpoſely conſecrated and ſet apart for publike worſhip. What then? I anſwer, that hee did declare the ceſſation of worſhip to be now at hand, both according to the cuſtome of the <hi>Iewes</hi> worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and of the Samaritans wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping upon the aforeſaid Mountaine. For all ſuch ſhadowes, types, and figures, as poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Meſſiah, muſt ceaſe, the body being come. And in that regard hee uſeth the word Spirit by way of oppoſition: or as it is ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that commandement, which [in <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.16.] is called carnall. And ſo alſo for the word truth; he ſpeaketh of it, not as wee ſet it againſt a lie, but as wee take it in reſpect of the outward ceremonies of the Law, which did only ſhadow that which Chriſt performed in very deed: as even the <hi>Geneva</hi> note obſerveth. Or if that of Spirit and truth bee further ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the better to colour mens want of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the houſe of God; it is againe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that when outward or corporall worſhip, proceedeth from ſpirituall devotion, and is applied thereunto, it is then a Spirituall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; becauſe, by this rule, it is joyned to that,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6542:13"/>which ought to bee the chiefe and principall mover in all our poſtures.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.2.</hi> q. <hi>84.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi> Ad primum.</note> And ſo ſaith <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, Quod etiam adoratio corporalis in ſpiritu fit, in quantum ex ſpirituali devotione procedit, &amp; adeam orainatur.</hi> And indeed, ſo long as man hath a body as well as a ſoule, how ſhall hee manifeſt his inward feare and reverence, but by his outward devotion? or ſhall the ſoule be ſubject, and the body free? 'Tis nothing ſo, hee that made both requireth (as the Apoſtle tels us) that we glorifie him in both. And ſo, outward reverence, as well as inward feare, doth neceſſarily belong to every Chriſtian. The true worſhippers therfore ſhould remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to addreſſe themſelves with dread and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and enter with preparation as unto God; proſtrating,<note place="margin">Eae quae exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius aguntur, ſigna ſunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terioris reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentiae. Aquin. ſum. <hi>2.2.</hi> q. <hi>84.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> or bowing downe their bodies; not only in token of their, both inward, and outward humiliation; but alſo in regard of the reverence which they owe to God, into whoſe houſe, and before whoſe preſence, they are now entred. And indeed it is an humble ſoule, that is both ready and willing to ſhew and afford due reverence: whereas the proud and haughty will rather kick againſt the pricks, and (<hi>Haman</hi>-like) expect, that all ſhould bow the knee to them, but they to none; no not willingly to him, who is the Lord almightie. But is it not written of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 2.19.</note> that when <hi>Bathſheba</hi> came unto him, notwithſtanding in dignitie ſhee was his inferiour, and then a peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6542:13"/>to him, that he aroſe from his throne, and bowed himſelfe unto her? Much more ought wee, that are worſe then nothing, to ſhew all humilitie and reverence, when wee come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the preſence of God. It is alſo written in the Goſpell, that our Saviour would not have his Diſciples enter into a mans houſe without ſalutation. And ſhall wee not thinke it to be a part of religious manners to doe as much when wee come into the houſe of God? when wee doe it, it is a kind of dutifull ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the divine Majeſtie. And therefore as wee count them to be rude and diſobedient, who will not bend their knees to their parents at their firſt approaches, nor bow their bodies to their betters when they come in place where they are: ſo be they both rude and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, who will not only refuſe, but diſpute the caſe, and ſcoffe againſt this kind of worſhip, or bowing of the body at our firſt entrings into the houſe of God. It were eaſie to ſhew, that all Nations and Religions, have beene carefull to expreſſe ſome reverentiall geſture at their firſt approaches into their Temples: and ſhall Chriſtians now make queſtion of it? We may bee too ſuſpitious of ſuperſtition, and ſo bee ſuperſtitious in avoyding that, which wee goe about to taxeand condemne in others.</p>
            <p>Nor is it but requiſite that I alſo ſhew, which way our poſture be directed. And ſo much the rather, becauſe (in the opinion not of a few)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6542:14"/>here reſteth that which is the greateſt queſtion. For what more frequent in the mouthes of many, then that ſuch as worſhip towards one thing, and place, rather then towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are meere Idolaters? But I beſeech you condemne not without a cauſe, nor let your zeale runne before your knowledge: For ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration towards the Lords Tables a lawfull worſhip. It can be no Idolatrie; becauſe it is no proſtration before a falſe god, but before the true; it being every jot as lawfull to make uſe of the place whither, as of the place where. So that either it muſt be unlawfull to uſe Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories or Churches to worſhip God in, or this muſt be granted of directing our Aſpect rather one way, then another. And why one way ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then another? wee ſhall find it to bee, in regard of that which is moſt ſacred, and of moſt eminent relation to God in the Church. For, as Gods houſe and honour goe together; ſo the chiefe place muſt needs invite the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God towards it, as to the moſt preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall place: otherwiſe wee ſhould exclude due decencie from Religion, and be prepoſterous in our worſhip; of which more ſhall be ſpoken afterwards.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Oh but ſay ſome, let the matter be palliated how it will; it is but an imitation of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, in their worſhipping of Images, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for themſelves that they doe not worſhip the Image, but God by the Image.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:6542:14"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> To which I anſwer, that to worſhip God by an Image, and to worſhip him towards ſome place and Monument of his preſence, are things of a different nature. The one is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely forbidden by the Law of God; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee find continually practiſed by his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with his allowance and approvement. Nor doth it ſeeme to have beene any other practiſe, then what was firſt done <hi>ex more generis huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni;</hi> as one in his letter to his friend hath truly expreſſed: Nature having taught them, as in their addreſſes to men to look unto their faces; So in their addreſſes to the divine Majeſtie, to accommodate their poſture towards ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, where his preſence was more declared and manifeſted, then elſe-where. Thus in the wilderneſſe, without any precept to bind them, they worſhipped God toward the Cloude, as the monument of his preſence going with them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.10. &amp; 34.5, 8. Then afterwards, when that monument was no longer, they loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked towards the Arke of the Covenant, or Mercie ſeate, both in the Tabernacle, and the Temple. And for this, it was no more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded then the former. There is indeed, in <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.22. a promiſe made to <hi>Moſes</hi> of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence there; which is enough to ſignifie, that the Lord hath his throne in the places which are ſet apart and ſanctified for his ſervice: But neither was the Tabernacle made, nor did <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> reveale any thing that was told him concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6542:15"/>it, till after ſuch times as wee are ſure they had worſhipped toward the Cloud. Nor laſt of all when it was erected, can it be any where ſhowne, that there went out a peculiar precept for ſuch a practiſe: And yet the very ſaints of God, whilſt they were alive (as well as thoſe in heaven who worſhip towards the Throne) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed the performance of it;<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.7. Pſal. 28.2.99.5.138.2. Jon. 2.4. Mich 6.6. 2 King. 18.22 See alſo 1 K. 8.44. Dan. 6.10. 2 Chron. 6.20, 21.</note> as in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Scripture well appeareth, ſome whereof are noted in the Margin. But among them all I may not forget that godly reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which was in the Prophet <hi>David;</hi> whoſe purpoſe was ſo ſetled concerning this, that let others be never ſo backward in it, hee would bee forward; Let others doe what they would; hee would doe what hee ought. The moſt expreſſe text of which intent is in the fifth Pſalme, at the ſeventh verſe, where his words be theſe:<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>But as for mee, I will come into thine houſe in the multitude of thy mercies; and in thy feare will I worſhip towards the Temple of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi> The word tranſlated, <hi>I will worſhip,</hi> is in the Hebrew, <hi>I will bow;</hi> and therefore <hi>Treme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> expreſſeth it by the Latine word, <hi>Incurva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo.</hi> By which the Prophet meaneth, that for his part, being come into the outward Courts of Gods houſe, into which (and no further) it was lawfull for him to enter, hee would bow towards the <hi>Sanctum ſanctorum,</hi> or chiefe place of Majeſtie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 99.5.</note> in honour of God, (as hee elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſheweth) whoſe houſe it was in all the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6542:15"/>parts; but there His in more particular: and therefore called, <hi>The Temple of his holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And may it not from hence be gathered, that they who would have all places in a Church to be alike holy, are greatly wide from the truth of the matter? I doe ſuppoſe it true: and ſhall make it more manifeſt, that they who would have the Belfree as holy as the body of the Church, the body of the Church as holy as the Chancell, the Chancell as holy as the <hi>Sacrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or Altar-place, are much miſtaken. For firſt, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſaid in another caſe, <hi>Doth God take care for oxen?</hi> So may I ſay in this: Doth God take care for Bells? or hath hee as much reſpect to them, as to thoſe things which are more immediately employed in his ſervice? I thinke him more ſtupid then a ſtone, who will beleeve it. There was a great difference ſure betweene the Aſh-pans and the Altars, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though both were holy: So alſo betweene the Bells and the Chalice. And if ſo: then alſo a difference betweene the Belfree, and the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: For all things and parts are not conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to one and the ſame height; as by and by ſhall bee declared. Secondly, by this their reaſoning of a like holineſſe in every part and corner of the Church, the holineſſe which they grant to bee in Churches, ſeemes in ſome ſort to be, as if it were inherent. But whether that bee the conſequence, yea or no, I will not ſtand to argue; for ſure I am, that in very deed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6542:16"/>there is no ſuch thing.<note place="margin">Aquin. Sum. p. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>83.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Churches (ſaith <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi>) and ſuch inanimate things, though they be not capable of grace, yet receive by their conſecration a ſpirituall power, whereby they are fit for divine ſervice.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore amplifie that, which I have already touched; namely, that the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence which wee give to one place above ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is onely relative; that is, in relation to thoſe holy offices unto which the places conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate are ſet apart: as alſo in relation to the preſence of God in places conſecrate. For to ſpeake of theſe things further, according to the Scripture phraſe, <hi>The face or preſence of God,</hi> doth in this ſenſe ſignifie [in the general] a peculiar ſacred place, where teaching, hearing, praying, ſacrificing, and other duties of Gods publike worſhip uſeth to be performed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by teaching us, that when wee come into Gods houſe, wee come as into his preſence. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of that which is ſaid in the 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.29. <hi>Bring an offering and come before him.</hi> In Pſal. 96.8. it is, <hi>Bring an offering and come into his Courts.</hi> I ſpeake not therefore of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and comfortable effects of his preſence:<note place="margin">Eſay 66.1, 2. Math. 18.20.</note> For they (according to his promiſe) are beſt of all manifeſted by the ſinceritie of our decent devotions: But I ſpeake of that high honour, which hee himſelfe vouchſafeth to ſuch places, as are dedicated to him for his publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> that they are accepted as his houſes;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6542:16"/>muſt bee ſo eſteemed; and comming into them, wee are come as before his face, or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred preſence, in more ſpeciall manner then when wee were in any place elſe. For though hee be <hi>ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> yet hee would not have us thinke, that hee is <hi>ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> uniformiter,</hi> but <hi>aliter at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> And in that regard, even in places conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate, one place may have a more neere relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his preſence then another, and carry with it (in particular) a more ſpeciall ſigne or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of his reſidence.</p>
            <p>And therefore, firſt of all, in caſe the Act of Conſecration bee but one, as ſome object; yet in relation to thoſe holy offices unto which the places conſecrate are ſet apart, it muſt needes admit of a different degree; becauſe as all places are not for one purpoſe, no more are all offices of a like eminence; And ſo, a more awfull reverence, both in, and towards one place then another. Yea, ſo farre were thoſe particular degrees of Conſecration evermore extended, that they belonged as well to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as to places; both when <hi>Moſes</hi> was upon the Mount, and the people below, the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle pitched, the Temple built, and the Prieſts aſſigned to their ſeverall charges.</p>
            <p>And as then, the ſeparation and difference obſerved redounded more and more to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God; ſo alſo now. For as there is no reaſon that the Lord ſhould loſe any part of his honour by ſending of his Sonne: So nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6542:17"/>would hee that it ſhould bee loſt. For Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe (who came to doe his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will) in whipping the buyers and fellers out of the very utmoſt borders of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſhewed his zealous forwardneſſe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of his Fathers honour: and, that in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture times, it ſhould (of right) be as well regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as before. For when he layed his hands to the whip, and his tongue to the text, it was no other time then after his Baptiſme, and at the very<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>viz.</hi> In the laſt weeke of his miniſtery, <hi>viz.</hi> on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day and Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day of the ſaid weeke, as the <hi>Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> witneſſe.</note> point of his paſſion, when he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to finiſh the worke of redemption, and when the legall ſacrifices, of Oxen, Sheep, and Doves, had<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 11.13. &amp; Galat. 3.24, 25.</note> begun (even from the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> preaching) to bee dead already. Whereby is ſhewed, that that holineſſe, and honour, which heretofore was due to Gods houſe, and to God in his houſe, ſhould not die with thoſe ending figures of the Law, but ſtill abide; extending it ſelfe, to the praiſe and glory of God, ſo farre as the benefit of Chriſts baptiſme and paſſion did; and ſhould live as long as either praying or preaching remained.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, although the Lord would have the whole ſtructure to bee accounted as his houſe, and would (doubtleſſe) that wee ſhould thereupon account him more preſent there,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.10.</note> then elſe-where; as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid, <hi>In the mountaine will the Lord bee ſeene:</hi> or, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſpeaketh;<note place="margin">Pſal. 132.15.</note> 
               <hi>Here will I dwell, for I have a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light therein.</hi> Yet his very preſence there, hath
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6542:17"/>not one and the ſame degree. For if when we ſay, <hi>Eſt Dominus in loco hoc?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lippom. in Gen. <hi>28.</hi> ex Auguſt.</note> Wee expound it with S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> that it is as if it ſhould be ſaid, <hi>Eſt hic demonſtratio domini; non enim Dominus in loco eſt:</hi> then it muſt needs follow (even in our Churches) that in what part or place, wee have the moſt lively demonſtration of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, by ſomething which is either done or ſaid there, more then elſe-where, as in a place,<note place="margin">Aquin. Summ. <hi>1.2.</hi> quaeſt. <hi>10.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and at an inſtrument appropriated for that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that there (I ſay) is the very higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree thereof; and ſo, the higheſt Court of (or for) his holineſſe: which is not unfitly called the place of Majeſtie, throne, or moſt preſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all place in all the Church. And although the particular ſervice be not alwayes there in act, yet the demonſtration ceaſeth not; becauſe the ſame place, and things, are reſerved ſtill for the ſame purpoſe, and Gods relative proprietie not aboliſhed: the great ſigne of his preſence ſtill abiding.</p>
            <p>Nor may this ſeeme ſtrange, that in one and the ſame houſe there ſhould bee ſuch differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced degrees of his Preſence: for, beſides the reaſons alledged, this we alſo find, that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is well pleaſed to call one part as the place of his Throne; another, as the place for the ſoales of his feet: as is expreſſy mentioned in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> chapt. 43.7.<note place="margin">Ezek. 43.7.</note> And this his old people alwayes marked; keeping their diſtances, and directing their poſtures accordingly.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6542:18"/>
            <p>In imitation whereof, the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ordered to have their Churches built with the like diſtinction of places; and, that though the diſtribution of the Sacrament, might be in other parts, yet the Conſecration thereof, might bee but in one, wherein ſtood the ſacred Altar or holy Table; which was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that Mercie-ſeate in the diviſion of the Temple: upon which it was a cuſtome to lay the booke of the holy Goſpels, in ſtead of the two Tables of the Law; and wee have there the holy Euchariſt, although the Pot of Manna be not now.</p>
            <p>And well might they imirate ſuch a plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme. For as the Chriſtian Religion is come in place of the Iewiſh: ſo are our Churches come in place of theirs. Their Tabernacle was a patterne of their Temple, and their Temple a type of our Churches, even as all their ſervice was a type of our Chriſt; as a learned Doctor hath delivered. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> is witneſſe to it: for though the Revelation be very miſticall; yet ſeeing the viſions of things appertaining to the Chriſtians, doe ſo frequently allude to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> it is eaſie to bee gathered, that hee inſinuates how wee are ſurrogated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their roomes for whom the Temple was built: and ſo, are to caſt the forme of our Churches after that faſhion: yea, and ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide their Types and Figures (which were ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in Chriſt) to ſerve God in our Holy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6542:18"/>places, and upon our Holy dayes, as they did in and upon theirs. I may therefore conclude, that ſtill there ought to be a place of Majeſtie; which by the Ancients was called either <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> or, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: The laſt of which two words, properly ſignifying a Chriſtian Altar, ſheweth, that the appellation of the place was derived from thence: that is, the Altar ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times gave the name to the whole place of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie: yea, and ſometimes (as ſome affirme) to the whole Chancell it ſelfe, though that only within the Raile were properly the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Sacrarium.</hi> And as for the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, <hi>Ignatius</hi> is an early one among them; Hee lived in the dayes of Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi> and writing no Propheſie, might ſpeake that plainly, which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> (as 'twas delivered to him) expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed myſtically.</p>
            <p>Or if you will that I open the matter more fully, then take it thus, <hi>viz.</hi> that becauſe Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> alludeth to the cuſtomes of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and delivers his Propheſie to the Chriſtians, and ſpeakes as if his Viſions were repreſented to him in the Heavens; it is as if it ſhould be ſaid, <hi>Gods Church is in it ſelfe but one, though the parts bee two, Militant and Triumphant:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as the Church of the <hi>Iewes</hi> was ordered according to the manner of theſe Viſions; So ought the Church of the Chriſtians, in all and every of the Congregations appertaining to her. And as it ought, ſo it was in thoſe her
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6542:19"/>dayes of greateſt puritie; ſtriving thereby to keepe as neere a reſemblance of the one part of Gods Church with the other, as ſhee poſſibly could; whether in the Heavens, or on the Earth. And in this the<note n="*" place="margin">At the 35. page of his booke.</note> authour of the Holy Table (though perhaps beyond the intention) gives us his voice. For, ſpeaking of the Kings Majeſties Royall Chappell (which is ordered according to the manner of thoſe forenamed Viſions) hee hath theſe words. <hi>I hope</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>I ſhall over live and die in an awfull and reverend opinion of that Sacred Oratorie, the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt reſemblance I know upon the earth of that Harmonie of the Cherubins wee looke for in the Heavens.</hi> Thus he: And it was truly ſpoke. Wherefore it is the more to bee admired, that hee ſhould eaſt any ſcornes or ſlights upon it afterwards, and not rather bee delighted to ſee all other of Gods houſes ordered according to ſo good a patterne: for what better Harmonie can there bee, then that the Church on Earth conforme her ſelfe to the Church in Heaven. And that thus ſhee hath done, in the dayes of old, both before and after Chriſt, ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. As for example: Firſt of all, in the Heavens S. <hi>Iohn</hi> witneſſeth that hee ſaw a Throne, and one that ſate upon it: So in the Temple (as formerly in the Tabernacle) was a Mercie ſeate, the ſacred Monument of Gods preſence there: And in the firſt Chriſtian Churches a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Sacrarium,</hi> incloſed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6542:19"/>with a Raile, for the Holy Table; the ſigne likewiſe of his Reſidence. Secondly, in the Heavens the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> or 24 Elders had the preheminence of comming neereſt to the Throne: So in the Tabernacle and Temple (as formerly at Mount <hi>Sinai</hi>) the people might not enter into the Courts of the Prieſts; Nor in the Primitive times was it lawfull for any Lay-man to come within the bounds of the Altar. <hi>Nulli omnium qui ſit in Laicorum nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, liceat intra ſacrum Altare ingredi,</hi> ſaith the 96 Canon of the ſixt Councell of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> The paſſages likewiſe betweene Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> and the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Theodoret,</hi> in his fifth booke, and ſeventeenth Chapter (beſides other teſtimonies) make it manifeſt. And laſt of all, <hi>In the Heavens hee ſaw the Elders, and foure living creatures fall downe and worſhip before the Throne,</hi> Revelat. 19.4. So, in the Tabernacle and Temple, holy men uſed to worſhip toward the Mercie ſeate, as they had done before towards the Cloud. Yea, and ſo alſo, in the firſt Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, they uſed to worſhip towards the Altar or Holy Table: For the Greeke Liturgies tell us of a threefold proſtration that was made before it: Nay ſooner yet; for Reverence done at it may be found by the learned, even in the dayes of that Antient already mentioned: I meane <hi>Ignatius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignat. ad Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſ.</hi> Act. 11.26.</note> who was made Biſhop of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> (where the Diſciples were firſt called
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6542:20"/>Chriſtians) not above ſeven and thirtie yeares after Chriſts Paſſion: hee was one of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> ſcholars,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Paenit. c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and died a godly Martyr. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> (who was flouriſhing about 163 yeares after the ſaid Paſſion) doth likewiſe teſtifie, that the Penitents uſed to fall on their knees before it. But did they therefore worſhip it? It were a ſhamefull accuſation to ſay they did. A man when hee ſayes Grace before his Table, or kneeles before his Bed, or other place, when hee makes his private prayers, may as well bee ſaid to worſhip either his Table or Bed, as theſe men bee ſaid to worſhip the Altar. Or thus, <hi>Daniel</hi> may as well bee accuſed for turning his face towards <hi>Ieruſalem, David</hi> for looking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Temple of Gods Holineſſe, the People for directing their aſpect towards the Cloud; Nay, the very Saints and Angels for falling downe before the Throne, as they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed who proſtrate or bow before the Altar. For as <hi>Daniel</hi> being in captivitie, although hee turned his face towards <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> when hee prayed, prayed not to it; nor <hi>David</hi> made the <hi>Temple of Gods Holineſſe,</hi> the object of his ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; nor the people in the Wilderneſſe jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Cloud to bee adored; nor the Saints and Angels in Heaven worſhipped the Throne, although they fell downe before it: So in bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or falling downe before Gods Altar, it is not the Altar,<note place="margin">Soerat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> but God that is worſhipped. Furthermore, <hi>Socrates</hi> alſo reporteth, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:6542:20"/>Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople, Ad Altare progreſſus, humi coram ſacra Menſa ſe in faciem proſtravit;</hi> meaning, <hi>that comming to the Altar, hee caſt himſelfe on his face, or bowed to the ground before that Holy Table.</hi> Or as<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> Hee who was the authour of the Holy Table, pag. 194. <hi>Sozom. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 28.</note> ſome tranſlate it out of the Greeke Copie, <hi>Hee came into the Quire or Chancell, and bowed before the Holy Table. Sozomen</hi> makes mention, that his proſtration was, when he came <hi>Ad Baſin Alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, at the foot of the Altar. Ad baſin Altaris procidens, totam noctem pronus humi jacebat.</hi> And in the dayes of the fift generall Councel, the Archbiſhop of the foreſaid place exhorted the people to doe their accuſtomed reverence, or to adore at the holy Altar. Alſo, in the dayes of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> the Emperour is put in mind of the difference of places. And againe, did not the reverence of Holy Altars prevaile ſo farre with the furious Souldiers, and barbarous <hi>Goths,</hi> that (as the ſaid <hi>Ambroſe</hi> telleth us) they willingly fell downe and kiſſed them?<note place="margin">Ambr. lib. <hi>5.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> And if you thinke that this act of their was more then needed; I anſwer, that there is an honour due likewiſe to the very things themſelves: which conſiſteth in a Veneration, or a reverent uſing of whatſoever belongeth to Gods Houſe; and chiefly of thoſe things which have moſt relation to his holy worſhip: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wee ſhould bee abſolute allowers of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation, and be (in a manner) as bad as thoſe, whom our Saviour himſelfe drove away
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6542:21"/>from out of his Fathers Houſe.</p>
            <p>More teſtimonies might bee alledged, but theſe are enough; and too many (perhaps) may ſome man thinke, who careth not to tread in the ſteps of the holy Fathers: And yet even the authour of the Holy Table thinketh, that they did it decently and devoutly; as may bee ſeene at the 193. page of his booke: affirming more fully, ſome certaine<note n="*" place="margin">See pag. 99.</note> pages before, that although the Canon doth not enjoyne it, yet reaſon, pietie, and the conſtant practiſe of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie doth. That Church-men doe it in Saint <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> Liturgie; and the Lay-men are commanded to doe it in Saint <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> Homilie; bequeathing them to <hi>Donatus,</hi> who can practiſe all manner of Curteſies for Maskes and Dances, but none (by any meanes) for Chriſt, at their approach to the Holy Table. Whereupon hee doth not ſo much accept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this kind of worſhip, as that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Table ſhould be called by the name of Altar: a poore quarrell; and ſuch as Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie knowes not how to countenance. It had beene good therefore if our Church had never beene troubled with ſuch verball contentions. But to give ſatisfaction in this, let us looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Antients for our better quiet.</p>
            <p>And firſt I will begin with the ſecond (or as ſome divide them) the third of the Apoſtles Canons, where the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Altar, is twice uſed for the Holy Table.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:6542:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ignatius</hi> alſo in his Epiſtles <hi>ad Philadelphen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Trallenſes,</hi> and <hi>Epheſies,</hi> hath the ſame word for the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> are well enough knowne to call the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iren. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>20. &amp;</hi> c. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> both an oblation and a Sacrifice: and therefore not to bee doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but that they called the place or ſeate thereof (as well as their Predeceſſours, and ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> likewiſe, in that teſtimonie of his already mentioned, as alſo in<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. in ſine.</note> other of his writings, uſed the word <hi>Altar for the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> in many of his Epiſtles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz. Epiſt.</hi> 42.55.64.70.73. &amp;c.</note> doth the like.</p>
            <p>So alſo doth <hi>Euſcbius,</hi> who lived in the daies of that famous <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> alſo,<note place="margin">Ambr. lib. <hi>5.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> who was in the dayes of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> (a ſecond <hi>Conſtantine</hi>) ſaith no leſſe.</p>
            <p>And in <hi>Gregorie Niſſen</hi> the like phraſe is<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz</hi> Serm. de baptiſmo. Quid eſt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare niſs ſedes corporis, &amp; ſanguinis Chriſti? Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> uſed.</p>
            <p>So alſo Saint <hi>Auſtin, Optatus,</hi> and generally ſo many others, as cannot without tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be related. Howbeit, this muſt be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred; that (as a worthy<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Meade in his</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ex Chryſoſt, Hom. Quod Chriſlus est Deus.</note> authour hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> affirmes it of our Britiſh Ilands; ſaying, <hi>The Britsſh Ilands, which lie out of this Sea, and are in the Ocean it ſelfe, have felt the power of the Word: for even there alſo Churches and Altars are erected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if in theſe teſtimonies the Apoſtles
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6542:22"/>Canons bee miſliked, it cannot bee in reſpect of the firſt of them; but rather that ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were added to them, and continued under the ſame title ſtill. Or, if the place of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> be objected, where hee ſaith,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.12</note> 
               <hi>You cannot communicate of the Table of the Lord, and of the Table of Divels:</hi> It is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that there is another place equall to it, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10. where hee alſo ſaith; <hi>Wee have an Altar whereof they have no right to eate, who ſerve the Tabernacle.</hi> Not that the materials of the Table or Altar can bee eaten: but that they who come to the holy Communion, partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of that which is there conſecrated, and from thence diſtributed. And indeed we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate from the Altar, as from an Holy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, of that heavenly banquet which in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper is afforded to us: And from the Table, as from an holy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, wee offer unto God the Memorie of that Sacrifice which his dearely beloved Sonne once offered upon the Croſſe. And ſo, though wee have neither any bloudy Sacrifice, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Iewes;</hi> nor any unbloudy propitiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Sacrifice, offered for the Quick and the Dead, as among the Papiſts: yet wee have a commemorative Sacrifice, done in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Chriſt, and of his death and Paſſion. And therefore one and the ſame thing may bee called both <hi>A Table</hi> and an <hi>Altar. A Table for the Lords Supper:</hi> and an <hi>Altar for the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6542:22"/>Sacrifice of our Lords death.</hi> Or will you have it yet more full and plaine? then know, that as the Apoſtle in the one place, calls the Altar of the Pagans by the name of Table; ſo in the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.21.</note> other place, hee calls the Table of the Chriſtians by the name of <hi>Altar.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> Heb. 13.10.</note> For as hee compares cating with eating; ſo alſo Altar with Altar, or Table with Table; uſing the appellation with indifferencie, as wee alſo find in ſome other places of the Booke of God, <hi>viz. Ezek.</hi> 41.22. and <hi>Malach.</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p>Nor againe, if things bee well weighed, can it but probably appeare, that Chriſt [in <hi>Math.</hi> 5.23.] taught Chriſtians, that even in the dayes of the Goſpell, there ſhould bee ſomething ſtill, which ſhould beare the name of Altar, in the holy place of their Aſſemblies: at which they might not offer, except they were in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect love and unitie one with another. For in that Sermon where this dutie is commanded, the Precepts given were not legall, but Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall; it being a degree above the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, to ſeeke ſuch peace as was then preached upon the Mountaine: No tradition of the Elders, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Law, being knowne to urge any ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, as was there delivered.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, conſidering one thing with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, it may bee concluded, as in a plaine caſe, that by both names that ſacred ſeate of the body and bloud of our Saviour, as <hi>Optatus</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:6542:23"/>ſtileth it, hath beene promiſcuouſly and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently called from the firſt beginning of the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>They goe wrong therefore who will be led by vulgar opinion, and aſtoniſhed by popular reports of they know not what. <hi>Rome</hi> indeed hath made many things offenſive to ignorant eares: But it is neither vulgar opinion, feare, nor heare ſay, that can diſprove a truth. For, as ſhee ſeekes no corners; ſo, being ſuffered to diſplay her colours, ſhee cleares her ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſorts of oppoſites, bee their temper what it will.</p>
            <p>To returne then to the matter in hand; <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie,</hi> and that grounded upon Scripture, takes from it (as well as from what is appendant to it) all and every juſt aſperſion of innovation. And verily thoſe Sainted times loved the great God of Heaven and Earth too well to love any thing like him. They knew him to bee a jealous God, and therefore did not adore the thing or place toward which they worſhipped, but God alone to whom this homage is due.<note place="margin">Juſt. Mart. ad Orthod. quaeſt. <hi>118. See alſo</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul Apol. c. <hi>16.</hi> Orig ſup. Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Hom. <hi>5.</hi> Baſil de ſpirit. ſanct. c. <hi>27.</hi> Aug. de Serm. Dom. in Mont. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi> cum mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is aliis.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot bee (ſaith <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi>) that at the time of our Prayer wee ſhould looke at all the parts of heaven at once; therefore we worſhip looking towards one part: [<hi>viz.</hi> the Eaſt.] Not that that is only of Gods making, or that hee hath choſen that only for his dwelling; but becauſe it is the place appointed for that worſhip and ſervice which wee performe to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6542:23"/>God. Adding moreover, that from whom the Church received the cuſtome of praying, from them alſo it received where to pray; that is, from the Apoſtles. Thus that godly Father and bleſſed Martyr, who was famous about 117 yeares after Chriſts Paſſion: expreſly wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing, that this order came firſt from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>viz.</hi> that Chriſtians direct their aſpect towards the Eaſt when they pray or worſhip. <hi>Tertullian</hi> witneſſeth the ſame order: and ſo doth <hi>Origen, Athanaſius, Baſil, Gregorie, Niſſen,</hi> Saint <hi>Auſtin, Damaſcen,</hi> with many others. Nor can the Centurie writers but affirme it; moſt of our Churches (excepting ſome of late) being built for ſcituation accordingly.</p>
            <p>From which direction thus delivered, was clearely ſhewed, that albeit in the Iewiſh Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle and Temple the Weſterne part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was chiefe; yet not ſo in the Chriſtian Churches: for in ours, the Eaſterne part muſt be preferred. And as with them the Weſterne part was chiefe, becauſe the Mercie ſeate was there: ſo with us the Eaſterne part, becauſe the Holy Table is placed here.</p>
            <p>And for the ſcituation of both theſe, there was juſt cauſe why they ſhould bee rather ſo then otherwiſe. For the <hi>Iewes</hi> wee know were in the times of darkneſſe, in compariſon of our times of light: Their Tabernacle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and Temple had the place of higheſt Majeſtie in the Weſt; towards which they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6542:24"/>looked for want of the Sunnes appearance, Chriſt was then unborne. But wee are in the dayes of a better light, the Sunne is riſen and viſiteth us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the Day, or Eaſterne light from on high, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.78. Wee therefore, in acknowledgement thereof, turne our faces toward the Eaſt, have there the place of higheſt Majeſtie, and by turning thither profeſſe our times to be the times of light.</p>
            <p>To which may be added that of <hi>Damaſcen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Damaſ. de Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. fid. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> affirming that when Chriſt hanged upon the Croſſe, hee was placed ſo as that his face loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked into the Weſt; and therefore could not be ſeene, but of thoſe whoſe faces were directed towards the Eaſt. Which, together with the former, was alſo a reaſon why the Chriſtians had cauſe to preferre the Eaſterne part of their Churches, before the Weſterne, and to place the Altar of their commemorative Sacrifice rather there, then elſe-where.</p>
            <p>Yea, and further, becauſe the Divell is Gods Ape, the <hi>Pagans</hi> looked into the Weſt as well as the <hi>Iewes.</hi> That therefore, (in oppoſition to the one as well as the other) wee may renounce the Divell whom they ſerved in their heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Idolatrie, as well as the religion of the <hi>Iewes</hi> who denie Chriſt to be come, wee turne to the Eaſt, and ſo enter a covenant with the Sunne of righteouſneſſe. And of this laſt, Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> (among other of the Fathers) ſpeakes after this manner: <hi>Thou art turned to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6542:24"/>the Eaſt, becauſe hee who renounceth the Divell, is converted to Chriſt, and beholds him,</hi> directo obtuitu, <hi>with a direct aſpect.</hi> Vnto which cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome (as is probably ſuppoſed) Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſeemeth to allude, in <hi>Revelat.</hi> 7.2. For there the Angell aſcends from the Eaſt, to meet and embrace them that looke towards him, and ſeale them with the ſafetie of that Sacrament by which Chriſtians ſeale their ſervice unto him; as in Maſter <hi>Yates</hi> is well obſerved. Here therefore wee are to ſeate the Holy Table, as in its proper place. Nor was it ever otherwiſe among Chriſtians, when they might bee ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to doe as they would, except in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches, which can be no fit preſident to be oppoſed againſt a generall practiſe.</p>
            <p>And thus as I can ſee no reaſon why any ſhould bee offended at a decent and holy reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence when wee come into the Houſe of God, which all Religions have beene carefull to performe: ſo, much leſſe, that they ſhould grudge againſt it, when wee doe it towards that place, where the high and heavenly Myſteries of our ſalvation are to be conſecrated, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated with all the ſolemnitie, and devotion wee can poſſibly imagine. Here it is that wee have our perfecteſt communion with God. It begins indeed in Baptiſme, but ends in the Lords Supper; (for higher wee cannot goe till wee come in heaven) and they are the beſt Saints that are admitted to it; at the leaſt wee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6542:25"/>judge them ſuch, becauſe ſuch they ſhould be. For though all may come to the Word, and be preſent at our ordinarie Service; yet when this commeth, all but the faithfull muſt bee gone. <hi>Ite, Miſſaeſt,</hi> was that which was ſaid of old: yea, and ſtill the unworthy are not to bee admitted; but the reſt invited to come and draw neere, that they may receive this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to their comfort, and have that high ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of being fed at Gods owne Boord with the body and bloud of his beloved Sonne.</p>
            <p>Say not therefore any longer, Why are not the Font, Deske, or Pulpit, as holy as the Table: for this is the higheſt advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that a Chriſtian hath: and although the Lord bee preſent in all his holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; yet here more ſpecially, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Holy Table or Altar muſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neceſſitie bee evermore taken as the great ſigne of his preſence, as carrying with it the higheſt relation thereunto. Shall we come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe houſes (ſaith one) and neere thoſe places, as wee come into a common Inne or Ale-houſe? is there no reſpect, no regard to be ſhewed in the one above the other? I thinke reaſon and diſcretion will teach us the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For (as another alſo ſpeakes) it is juſt that that place have a preheminence above the reſt, from which vertue and efficacie is derived to the reſt: for all benefits and mercies to bee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6542:25"/>diſpenſed to us, come from the death of Chriſt, which (as is moſt certaine) is repreſented there.</p>
            <p>This place therefore may bee well eſteemed as a Mercie Seate, where God (according to his being in ſuch holy places) may bee ſaid to ſit, graciouſly reconciling a ſinner to himſelfe by the bloud of his Sonne. For though in Baptiſme there bee ſome externall reſemblance of Chriſt crucified; yet here more fully: and therefore ſpecially commanded to bee done in memorie of his Paſſion. Yea here (I ſay) the ſpeciall place of Majeſtie, and that ſo, as it may be well eſteemed as a Mercie ſeate. For in briefe, (that I may recapitulate the ſumme of all;) Firſt, as even that thing or place, which is dedicated to the higheſt office in our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or to the moſt ſacred Myſterie of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, muſt needs be the Moſt holy; although not by any internall inherent qualitie infuſed, transforming the nature of it: but by an exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall adherent qualitie, in relation to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe about which it is uſed, or for which it is ſet apart: So alſo ſecondly, In what part or place wee have the moſt lively demonſtration of his Preſence, there muſt be the very higheſt degree thereof; and ſo, the higheſt Court of (or for) his Holineſſe: wherein the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance or Monument of his Reſidence ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, not as an Image, but as a ſigne or teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie; even as the Arke was the ſigne of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6542:26"/>in the Temple. For now the greateſt ſigne of Gods reſidence in his holy place, is the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, or Holy Table, (call it which you will;) even as the Arke was heretofore the ſigne of his preſence in the Temple. Toward this part therefore (I ſay) a more awfull reverence is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, then towards, or in any other part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. For in a word to ſhut up this, although it were griefe enough to the ancient Chriſtians to ſee any part of their Churches violated or prophaned by the Pagans; yet, that they ſhould violate this <hi>Holy Place,</hi> was a great <hi>Cordolium</hi> indeed, and did augment their ſorrow to the very full. Whereupon Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines after this manner, writing to <hi>Innocent</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome. Neither was here</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>an end of thoſe things: for the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers entred even into the very Sanctuarie; Some whereof wee know were not ſo much as initiated in Divine Myſteries: and there they ſaw thoſe things which were within; Yea, and the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bloud of Chriſt was ſpilt upon the garments of the foreſaid Souldiers: as it falleth out in ſuch a tumult.</hi> And thus much for Reverence in entring.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified"/> THE next concernes our Deportment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entred, all the time the Service is in doing. Now this muſt bee ſuch as becommeth thoſe, who either ſpeake unto God, or have God ſpeaking unto them. For as in hearing God
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6542:26"/>commeth neere unto us; ſo in Prayer we come neere unto him. And if ſo (as ſo it is) then ſurely bold and lazie poſtures are unſufferable; and irreverent geſtures more then unſeemely. Some may not ſit, when others ſtand; or ſcorne to bend when others kneele.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (who would have all things to bee done decently and in order) forbids the covering of the head; and would, that hee who made the whole man, ſhould bee worſhipped of the whole. For, as wee muſt ſhew our faith by our workes; in like manner our inward humiliation, devotion, and honour to our God, muſt bee ſure to appeare in our<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.20.</note> outward geſtures, and comely po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures at his holy ſervice. God expects that we ſerve in both; ſoule and body. For as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond without the firſt is a dead oblation; ſo the firſt without the ſecond, is but a maimed offering. Which agrees to that of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in another place, <hi>With the heart man beleeveth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.101</note> 
               <hi>and with the tongue hee confeſſeth.</hi> Or more plainly, to that of <hi>David, Oh come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 95.6.</note> 
               <hi>let us wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and fall downe, and kneele before the Lordour Maker.</hi> Or (if you will) to that of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> yet once againe; ſaying:<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>I beſeech you brethren by the mercies of God, that yee give up your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes [as well as your ſoules] a living ſacrifice.</hi> The ſecond Precept ſpeakes as much: For, if wee may not bow unto an Image, becauſe God is a jealous God; then (without queſtion) we muſt, in ſuch parts of his ſervice as require it,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6542:27"/>bow and fall downe when wee worſhip Him. Did not the Divell therefore thinke it a great point of honour to have our Saviour ſhew his worſhip and reverence towards him, by falling down in worſhiping of him? He did not ſay, It ſufficeth if thou wilt but inwardly adore me.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 4.9.</note> But, <hi>All theſe will I give thee, if thou wilt fall downe and worſhip mee.</hi> And in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,<note place="margin">Revel. 4.10.</note> as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw it repreſented to him, is not God worſhipped by the bowings (or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings downe) of thoſe that bee there? Verely (as I have already ſhewed) Heaven is alwayes like it ſelfe. The Church Militant is a kind of heaven upon earth: and therefore the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations in it, muſt imitate the Aſſemblies which are Triumphant.</p>
            <p>Here wee muſt take no knowledge of either Father or Mother, Maſter or Dame, or other of our Betters, ſo as wee leave Gods ſervice, and riſe from our knees to honour them. For they that doe thus, ſeeme to ſay to God Almightie; <hi>Stay a while, I ſhall bee for thee againe anonne: My Maſter and Miſtris are not yet in their ſeates; I am now ſtanding up unto them, and will by and by kneele downe againe unto thee.</hi> But whoever they bee who have uſed to doe thus, muſt (if they doe as they ought) doe ſo no more. For if they doe, they preferre the Creature before the Creatour, and reverence their Maſter above their Maker. For 'tis a Rule, that when the dutie which wee owe to God, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6542:27"/>the dutie which wee owe to Man, ſtand in competition both together, we muſt then leave all, Father and Mother, Maſter and Miſtris, to waite upon God. <hi>Have yee not houſes to eate and to drinkein; Deſpiſe yee the Church of God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: although in another caſe. So may I ſay in this; <hi>There bee other times and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places to ſhew your dutie and reſpect to Man: But now remember your ſelves; you are met together for the ſervice of God. And if ſo, then in aword, There muſt be nothing either ſaid or done, which may make us forget the buſineſſe wee come for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Oh but doe I not heare ſome object, that theſe poſtures or geſtures which are uſed [as bowing, kneeling, and ſtanding up] are but outward Ceremonies, and humane civilities; ſuch as are not ſeldome applyed unto Men: and therefore farre unfit for God, who would have the true worſhippers to worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I have in ſome ſort given anſwer to this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. But that nothing be wanting, it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwered; namely, that when wee applie theſe geſtures unto God, they are changed in their nature from what they were when wee applyed them unto Men. They were then ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill honours; but are now to bee accounted acts of holineſſe. For it is a Rule, that acts are ſpecified according to their object, and end. Now then, in theſe, the object is God, and his glorie their higheſt end. For albeit the Lord,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6542:28"/>in reſpect of himſelfe, ſtands in no need of this; becauſe of himſelfe hee is all glorie, to whom no creature can adde any thing: yet, in regard of us, it ought to be done; who doe thereby acknowledge our owne meaneneſſe and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and teſtifie that reverent and religious eſteeme which wee have of his divine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; to whom, and not unto our ſelves, all the higheſt degrees of glorie that can be imagined, are of all creatures to bee aſcribed: And ſo, what Ceremonie ſoever is beſt able to expreſſe this, is the moſt commendable, and beſt beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming us in our Devotions. Nor is it (among true worſhippers) but a ſpirituall, as well as a bodily worſhip. For (as before was ſaid) <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily worſhip is performed in ſpirit,</hi> inaſmuch as it proceeds from ſpirituall Devotion, and is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to it. Yea, and being ordered thereunto, it cannot but prove an adjuvant cauſe to edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: For even by outward ceremonies, and ſenſible ſignes, our mind is incited to tend to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Lord. And therefore, <hi>Oh come, Let us worſhip and fall downe, and kneele before the Lord our Maker,</hi> is an excellent invitation at the beginning of the publike Service.</p>
            <p>But I haſten further, becauſe I deſire to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine ſome other things; as ſtanding up at <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Patri,</hi> at the Goſpell, at the Creed: and ſhall alſo ſpeake of Bowing at the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and of the Anſwers required in the Liturgie. For all theſe things are ſuch, as fall within the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6542:28"/>compaſſe of this third thing, which concernes our Cariage or Deportment.</p>
            <p>And firſt of ſtanding at <hi>Gloria Patri;</hi> it was a long while ſince obſerved, and was a generall cuſtome to ſtand up at it, in all the Churches of <hi>France:</hi> And this, above one thouſand and two hundred yeares from hence. For <hi>Caſsian,</hi> who flouriſhed about the yeare of our Lord God<note n="*" place="margin">Helvic. in Chronol.</note> 430, makes<note n="*" place="margin">Caſſiauus Inſtit. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> mention of ſuch an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Where note firſt of all, that it is no late innovation; but an antient practiſe. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as it is ancient; ſo alſo a geſture com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable and pious: for it is a ſigne that wee give ſmall glory to the Trinitie, when wee doe it ſitting, and ſhew no more token of reverence to the higheſt Majeſtie, then as if wee were <hi>haile fellow well met,</hi> or companions to the God Almightie.</p>
            <p>Nor ſecondly, is it Popiſh or ſuperſtition,<note place="margin">Standing at the Goſpel.</note> to riſe from our ſeates at the reading of the Goſpell. For it is in regard of the authour of the ſpeech, which is our Lord Chriſt: whom wee bleſſe and magnifie for his glorious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: giving thankes alſo to God the Father, for ſending of his Son to be the publiſher, and declarer, of ſuch good things, as are contained therein; from whom the Miniſtery thereof is appointed untill the end of the world, to bring men out of darkneſſe into light, that they may
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6542:29"/>be ſaved. Whereupon it is, that wee doe not only ſtand up whilſt the Prieſt readeth it, but alſo uſe to utter certaine words of acclamation; as <hi>Glorie be to thee O Lord,</hi> at the beginning: and at the end, theſe, or the like words follow; <hi>Thankes be to God for his glorious Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why wee doe not ſo at the reading of the Leſſons, is becauſe the reaſon of doing thus, holds not ſo fully there as here. For the Goſpels are more ſelect places then the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and doe moſt commonly declare hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, ſomething or other which our Saviour either ſpake, did, or ſuffered in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for us moſt miſerable ſinners. That incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>Hooker</hi> gives the like reaſons; as may be better ſeene in his owne writings.</p>
            <p>Now who can find any harme at all in any one of theſe orders?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Polyd. Virg. de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>8 and</hi> Calviſ. anno <hi>398.</hi>
               </note> Is there not rather a great deale of good? The laſt of which is alſo very ancient: for I find that there was a Law made concerning it; about the yeare of our Lord 400. which is now 1237 yeares ſince.</p>
            <p>Alſo,<note place="margin">Standing at the Creed.</note> concerning our ſtanding at the Creed; well is it that ſo wee doe. For this is a poſture which we uſe in teſtification of our faith, and allegiance to Chriſt our Generall; as our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Poſtiller hath declared. For as wee may know who is the Captaine of ſuch or ſuch a Souldier, when wee ſee his Colours: ſo a Chriſtian, by this authentique Creed, is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6542:29"/>from either <hi>Iew, Turke, Atheiſt,</hi> or <hi>Heretick.</hi> In token whereof it hath beene a long and laudable Cuſtome in the Church of God, to ſtand up at the rehearfall of it, openly to manifeſt our faith and allegiance to Chriſt Ieſus our Generall, <hi>viz.</hi> that we will not ſhrink backe from Him; but ſtand and acquit our ſelves like men, in the defence of that faith, which he hath taught us, in ſpight of all that ſhall oppoſe it.</p>
            <p>And next,<note place="margin">Bowing at the name of Ieſus.</note> as for bowing at the name of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> it is no ſuperſtition: but (as the ſeed-plats of the Church, I meane thoſe two famous Lights of our Land, the two Vniverſities have determined) an outward ſigne of our inward ſubjection to His divine Majeſtie, and an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent token of our devotion. Or thus: It is to teſtifie and declare our ſubmiſſion to Ieſus Chriſt in that exaltation wherewith God the Father hath exalted him, as a recompence for that profound humilitie, and compleate obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which he ſhewed and performed. For (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in that text,<note place="margin">Philip. 2.8, 9, 10, 11.</note> in which this dutie is commanded) ſeeing he humbled himſelfe, and became obedient to the death, even the death of the Croſſe; therefore hath God alſo highly exalted him, and given him a name above every name, <hi>That at the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus every knee ſhall bow, &amp;c.</hi> So that here it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that this honour is aſſigned to him as a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6542:30"/>part of his reward<note n="*" place="margin">See Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> Serm upon <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Propter mortem crucis, for the death of the Croſſe,</hi> For whereas the chiefe Prieſts, Scribes, and Elders, at the time of his death<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 27.37.40.</note> mocked him (in alluſion to his name) ſaying, <hi>Hee ſaved others, himſelfe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſave:</hi> and whereas the <hi>Iewes</hi> and wicked Miſcreants have alwayes ever ſince derided the Chriſtians with their crucified Ieſus; it pleaſed the Lord in his wiſdome to exalt his Name ſo much the more, by how much it was debaſed, and vilified by wicked men. And this hee would ſhould be expreſſed by ſome externall geſture, thereby to ſhew the inward obeyſance and ſubjection which is due to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Againſt which whilſt ſome object, that it cannot be meant of any actuall bowing of the knee; becauſe Angels, Soules departed, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, and damned ſoules have no knees to bow, they doe but deceive themſelves. For the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, ſpeaking unto men, ſpeakes after the manner of men; giving us to underſtand, that as wee are to ſhew our reverence and ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by bowing of the knee; ſo they, by ſome ſuch geſture as is truly correſpondent to this of ours. Wee know that in<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.1</note> another place, hee gives the Angels tongues; And therefore may as well in this place give them knees: They have the one as well as the other; And ſo in their kind, doe what is here commanded us. They their way; wee ours: for there be many paſſages in the<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 4.10.2.5.8. &amp;c. 14.7.11. See alſo Heb. 1.6.</note> Revelation which may cleare this doubt.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:6542:30"/>
            <p>And albeit ſome of theſe, of whom the Text ſpeaketh, be of a different quality from the ſaints and Angels, and are therefore obſtinately bent againſt Chriſt Ieſus, and will not for the preſent do their Reverence, nor be willing to ſhew any outward token of ſubjection, or obedience; yet, ſeeing Chriſt muſt reigne till he have put all his enemies under his feet,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.25.</note> the time ſhall be ſure to come, when the ſtrongeſt oppoſites ſhall bee brought unto it, and (whether they will or no) be made to ſtoope, and to do open reverence to that bleſſed name, which hath bin ſo often ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and derided by the Devils and wicked. And therefore, let every one that liveth bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, even how he leanes to perverſneſſe, leſt he come at laſt to be accounted guiltie of a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate evill: For when we have done the beſt wee can, it is no whit more then Chriſt hath meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For worthy is the Lambe that was ſlaine to receive power, riches, wiſdome, ſtrength, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, glorie, and bleſſing, <hi>Revelat.</hi> 5.12.</p>
            <p>Beſides, were it ſo that this were not ſpoken properly in reſpect of us, who have knees; it may as well bee granted, that neither is it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us that wee ſhould confeſſe: for the one is mentioned in the text of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> as well as the other. So that if wee take away the proprietie of ſpeech from the one, wee take it alſo from the other,; and then, wee are as little bound to confeſſe, as to bow: which were a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net directly oppoſite to a knowne truth. For,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6542:31"/>as with the heart Man beleeveth, ſo with the tongue he confeſſeth; as the Scripture elſewhere ſpeaketh, viz. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9, 10.</p>
            <p>Nor againe is there cauſe to feare, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee bow at the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and not at the name of God, that wee doe thereby advance the Sonne above the Father. For firſt, this honour of Chriſt begins with the Father: hee was the cauſe of it: by Him was his Sonne exalted, both in his perſon and his name, which hee would ſhould bee acknowledged: and therefore (ſaith the text) <hi>every knee ſhall bow, and every tongue confeſſe.</hi> And ſecondly, as it began with him, ſo it ends with Him alſo: for (ſaith the text againe) <hi>It is unto the glorie of God the Father.</hi> And no marvell: for it redounds much to His glorie, that wee ſhould thus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his Sonne. It is no will-worſhip taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our owne heads: but ſuch, as even the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther himſelfe both deſireth ſhould bee done; and is not only well pleaſed that it be done, but alſo glorified in regard that it is done. From whence it appeareth, that this bowing to the Sonne, is in effect a bowing to the Father alſo, at whoſe command, and unto whoſe glorie we doe it.</p>
            <p>And although it be in it ſelfe a dutie of the text, yet hath the Church alſo interpoſed her authoritie for the more ſtrict and decent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it.<note place="margin">Canon 18. Injunct. 52.</note> In which, neither doth our preſent Canon, nor that Injunction of Queene
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6542:31"/>
               <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> cauſe more to bee done then what had formerly beene obſerved in the Church of God, in thoſe ancient times which had beene before. For when they ſpeake of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence done at the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> theſe words are alſo mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> as it hath beene accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed.</p>
            <p>Nor was it a late cuſtome among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: for even in the dayes of Saint <hi>Hierom.</hi> the Chriſtian Church was carefull to obſerve it. His words bee theſe:<note place="margin">Hier. in Iſa. <hi>45.23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Moris enim Eccleſiaſtics eſt, Chriſto genuflectere: quod Iudaei, mentis ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biam demonſtrantes, omnino non faciunt. For it is</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>the cuſtome of the Church to bow the knee to Chriſt: which the Iewes, ſhewing the perverſneſſe of their mindes, altogether refuſe to doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it was then: but how long before, I cannot tell. Only this I obſerve from hence, that the ancient Church underſtood that text, where this dutie is taught, in the ſame ſenſe that we underſtand it now. And therefore, how they can bee acquitted from enemies of the Orthodox veritie, who feare not to ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, no man (I ſuppoſe) is able to declare: And ſooner by farre may they bring forth an argument of ſpight, then an evidence of the ſpirit, who ſpeake againſt it.<note place="margin">The people muſt uſe the Anſwers of the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The next dutie that I ſhall mention, is, that being in Gods houſe, and at his ſervice, care
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6542:32"/>muſt bee had to uſe all the Anſwers of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Liturgie; and that cheerefully and aloude: not whiſpering, or betweene the teeth: nor (as ſome doe) ſilently, and not at all. For tell me (I beſeech you) where is the eagerneſſe of your Prayers and Prayſes, if in a publike Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie yee bee as mute as fiſhes?<note place="margin">Revel. 14.2.</note> 
               <hi>I heard a voice from heaven</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>as the ſound of many waters, and as the ſound of a great Thunder and I heard the voyce of Harpers harp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their harpes.</hi> Like unto which ſhould bee the voyce of the Church on earth, in all her ſeverall Congregations, when ſhee uttereth her Prayers and Prayſes to the God of heaven. For firſt, wee are to come joyntly to the place of publike meeting, like the concourſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waters; whoſe voyce ſtands to ſignifie the voyce of a numerous, and full multitude, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing met together. Secondly, to bee earneſt in our devotions, like the ſound of a great Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And then thirdly, ſhall this loude voyce of ours bee muſicall, like unto thoſe heavenly Harpers harping with their harpes. It may be, <hi>Multa vox ex Pſallentium multitudine, ſed dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctabilis ex conſonantie ſuavitate:</hi> which is true, both in ſinging and in other parts of Gods ſervice.</p>
            <p>And verely, it was the praiſe of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church (in whoſe ſteps is the beſt footing) to doe all this, joyntly and aloud: inſomuch, that as (Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> ſpeaketh) their <hi>Amen</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:6542:32"/>was like a clap of Thunder; as is here ſignified: and their <hi>Halleluia,</hi> as the roring of the Sea.</p>
            <p>I ſhould bee glad therefore to ſee the people joyne with their Miniſter, both in heart and voyce; and to let ſo cheerefall and ſo good a light ſhine forth before men, that thereby the forwardneſſe and alacritie of one, may ſtirre up the dull drooping ſoule of another; and ſo, all bee as they ſhould, in the Houſe, and at the ſervices of God. And thus much for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment being entred.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, as wee may not bee Late Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, nor Ill Enterers,<note place="margin">We muſt not depart till all be ended.</note> nor of Ill Deportment being entred; So neither may wee be ſuch gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die-headed Fugitives, as to bee gone away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole ſervice bee fully ended. For, in the judgement of S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt-hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnend. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia.</note> 
               <hi>Hee is no better then a Fugitive, who takes his leave before the time come that hee bee diſmiſſed.</hi> Nay, ſhould hee goe to a Theatre, hee would ſcarce be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſuch a quick departure: but would firſt expect his <hi>Valete &amp; plaudite,</hi> and then depart. And is not the Prieſts bleſſing (beſides the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that he goeth from) of a farre greater conſequence? Prophane men and women, thus to diſhonour the God of heaven! Oh tell it not abroad, but to terrifie theſe idle and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie worſhippers. They preferre their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires before Gods ſervice: and ſo, in effect, make any thing elſe their God, rather then the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6542:33"/>Lord: How elſe could they ſhew ſuch an irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome aſſent to his holy worſhip?</p>
            <p>But 'tis not unknowne what was the cenſure for this offence, in the dayes of old. From the firſt words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (in which the peoples ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent attention was called for) untill the laſt words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Dimiſsio populi,</hi> they might not depart: it being a cenſure no leſſe then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication to bee gone away before the end; excepting in caſes of extreame neceſſitie. Thus in the Greeke Church. And in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine there was <hi>Ite, Miſſa eſt,</hi> twice pronounced by the Deacon: once, when the <hi>Catechumeni</hi> were ſent away; and once at the end of the Communion, after the whole Service was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ended. Our<note n="*" place="margin">Can. <hi>18.</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Anglic. <hi>See alſo</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. <hi>4</hi> Carth. &amp; Concil. Aurel. Can. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> Canon therefore doth not ill beſeeme us, which treads ſo neere ſuch pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous times.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing it is in the power of the Church to make ſuch Lawes, let it bee in the conſcience of the officers to ſee them kept. Yea, in a word; as wee pray that God would heare us, and goe not farre from us: ſo, by the like rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wee are to bee carefull that wee runne not away from Him. For it is but juſtice, that God deale with us, as wee with Him. And if wee forſake, or flie his Houſe on earth, no marvell if hee will not ſuffer us to enjoy the faire beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of it in the glorions heavens. In ſuch a caſe as this, the complaint can bee no ſooner taken up; <hi>Lord, why haſt thou forſaken us?</hi> but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6542:33"/>the anſwer will be as ready; <hi>Oh wicked and ſlothfull ſervant! why haſt thou forſaken mee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſt of all, as for Reverence in departure, they are ill adviſed who ruſh out together like an heard of cattell. For when all was done, <hi>They bowed themſelves and worſhipped.</hi> Their laſt poſture being like their firſt: as the<note n="*" place="margin">See 2 Chro. 29.29.</note> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alſo beare us witneſſe.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" rend="hr"/>
            <p>ANd now after all this, there is one thing more would be obſerved, namely, that wee ever remember for whom this Houſe is ſet apart. If it bee once Gods Houſe, 'tis alwayes ſo: as well when no aſſemblie is there preſent, as when the Service is in doing. For by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of divine proprietie, as it is alwayes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſo alwayes His. And this comes to paſſe in regard of the Dedication or Conſecration thereof to the divine Majeſtie. For when a thing is once dedicated or conſecrated to the Lord, the proprietie thereof becomes ſo His, as it is no longer Ours. Yea, thus to be Gods, is to be His in a peculiar manner, and not as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things are.</p>
            <p>And for all this wee have ſufficient warant; Firſt in the goods of the Church; as in that example of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphyra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4.</note> in the Acts of the Apoſtles. The goods were their owne, before they had devoted them: but then they
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6542:34"/>nothing appertained to them. Secondly, in the Veſſels and Vtenſils of the Church; as was ſeene,<note place="margin">Dan. 5.23. <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 12.13. and <hi>Sozom. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 7. Math. 21.12. Ioh. 2.14.</note> not only in that example of <hi>Baltha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> but in that alſo of the wretched <hi>Felix,</hi> and filthy <hi>Iulian.</hi> And laſt of all, in the very place it ſelfe; as our Saviours act (beſide other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples) hath well declared.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is more then manifeſt, that they are in a great errour, who would have Churches holy no longer then the time of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service. For, as there is alwayes a great difference betweene a Prieſt and a Lay-man; So alwayes a great difference betweene a Church and another place.</p>
            <p>Which [to conclude with] affords us theſe two Leſſons. Firſt, that wee are at all times ſo to behave us in Gods houſe, as that wee be more reverend there then elſe-where. It is the place where his honour dwelleth:<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.8.</note> and to bee uncovered in the Kings preſence Chamber, is an uſuall thing, though the King bee not there. It ſhould bee as uſuall to doe the like, much rather, in the Houſes of God, though the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie of ſervice bee not then: For there can bee but little love to God, when rudeneſſe takes place of reverence, and ſequeſters our reſpect from ſuch perſons, things, and places, as belong unto Him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if it bee Gods houſe, it cannot bee alſo thine, wee may not pervert or turne it to any ſecular employment. For though the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6542:34"/>Divel deale cunningly, and perſwade (what hee can) the contrarie; yet let it not bee thy fate to bee thus dangerouſly miſ-led by ſuch a Lyar. For, as hee deales falſely when hee would have us beleeve, that wee may retaine God in our hearts together with our ſinnes: So hee deales as deceitfully when hee would have us thinke, that Gods Houſe may ſerve for other uſes beſides his ſervice. Retort it therefore back againe; that as God, when hee calls to Man for his heart, meaneth not that the World, the Fleſh, and the Divell ſhould have one part, and hee another: but meaneth that it bee all for himſelfe: So, if it bee Gods houſe, hee muſt and will have it all alone. Before it was built to bee an houſe to thy God, the ground and coſt were thine owne, and thou mighteſt have done with them what thou wouldeſt; as in that before of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Ananias:</hi> But when thou haſt once given them to God, it is no more Thine, but His houſe. Yea, and ſo His, as that it be ſolely His. Hee loves no partner; nor is delighted with the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of a rude and wicked Prophaner: for <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe becommeth thine houſe for ever;</hi> as it is in the 93 Pſalme, at the 6 verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But bee there no times, nor no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, wherein things ſacred may be applied to a common uſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There be, I grant, ſome caſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Lord will have mercie, and not ſacrifice:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6542:35"/>but it is not for every one to judge of that. Howbeit, this I may ſay; that Charitie is a maine piece of pietie: and in that regard, holy things cannot bee properly ſaid to bee propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, when wee are forced to make them ſerve to the neceſſities of our Brethren; as was ſeene in <hi>David</hi> [<hi>Math.</hi> 12.] when hee, and they that were with him, went into the houſe of God, and did eate the Shewbread, as alſo in that of ſome of the Fathers, who were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to ſell a part of the holy Veſſels for the ſafetie of the needie. And in like caſe, I thinke, the Church is not prophaned, though wee be ſhut up there, for our better ſafetie; if, when wee are there, we doe not that which may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane it.</p>
            <p>But what's all this to that unſufferable li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie which ſome men take, either in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it a place to teach a Schoole, to lay lumber in, or a place for Iuries to conſult to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at their Courts and Leets, or a place for neighbours to come and commune in about their Seſſes or other compoſitions, or for a prophane Glaſier to mend his glaſſe upon the holy Table, or to ſay (as hath been ſometimes) that Playes and Enterludes may bee acted there? No: Theſe, and the like, are farre from that which may bee done in ſuch a place. And therefore, as Chriſt whipped the Buyers and ſellers from the Temple, overthrew the Tables of the money-changers, and ſeates of them
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6542:35"/>that ſold Doves: So ſhould every Chriſtian Church, zealouſly expell all ſuch kinds of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane doings from the Houſes of God: For it cannot but bee well pleaſing to the owner of them, to ſee his honour thus advanced. And, God bee thanked, wee have thoſe among us, who are tenderly affected towards it. The Lord make them proſperous: and never let them prevaile (oh Lord) whoſe factious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings declare too well, that they love to trouble the harmleſſe peace of their Holy Mother.</p>
            <closer>Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:6542:36"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6542:36"/>
            <p>Perlegi hunc Tractatum, cui titulus <hi>Propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no-Maſtix,</hi> dignum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> judico quitypis man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Wykes <hi>R. P. Epiſc. Lond. Capell. domest.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Octob 17. 1638.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6542:37"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6542:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
